Identification Information: 
  Citation: 
    Citation Information: 
      Originator: Alberta Energy Regulator
      Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
      Originator: Brinsky, J.
      Originator: Singh, A.
      Originator: Hauck, T.E.
      Originator: Grobe, M.
      Originator: Palombi, D.
      Publication Date: 2022
      Title: Subsurface Temperature Model of Alberta: Input Data (tabular data, tab-delimited format)
      Geospatial Data Presentation Form: tabular digital data
      Series Information: 
        Series Name: Digital Data
        Issue Identification: DIG 2021-0029
      Publication Information: 
        Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
        Publisher: Alberta Geological Survey
      Other Citation Details: We thank Jacek Majorowicz and his colleagues for allowing the temperature data produced at the University of Alberta during the Helmholtz-Alberta Initiative and his prior research to be included in our data compilation for this study.
      Online Linkage: http://ags.aer.ca/document/DIG/DIG_2021_0029.zip
  Description: 
    Abstract: This data release contains temperature data used to create a 3D subsurface temperature model for Alberta's deep subsurface (depths >1000 m). The main sources of data are:

1. A previously unpublished temperature database produced at the University of Alberta during the Helmholtz-Alberta Initiative as part of a data sharing agreement with the Alberta Geological Survey (AGS). This dataset consists of measured temperatures from drillstem tests and annual pool pressure survey reports, as well as Horner-corrected wireline log bottomhole temperature (BHT) data.

2. A database of uncorrected BHTs which was compiled from an AGS legacy dataset produced by manually transcribing log header data from microfiche logs, and combined with BHT data newly extracted from Log ASCII Standard (LAS) well log header data.

The uncorrected BHT data have been corrected using an Alberta-calibrated Harrison correction and have undergone a statistical culling process to compile this dataset.

Additional details regarding the methodology of assembling this dataset can be found in the methodology section of AGS Open File Report 2021-05: Temperature Mapping of Select Devonian Strata in Alberta.
    Purpose: For computer display, query, and modelling of temperature data for Alberta's subsurface from depths of 1000 m to the top of the Precambrian basement.
    Supplemental Information: Language: In English.
  Time Period of Content: 
    Time Period Information: 
      Range of Dates/Times: 
        Beginning Date: 1900
        Ending Date: 2019
    Currentness Reference: ground condition
  Status: 
    Progress: Complete
    Maintenance and Update Frequency: None planned
  Spatial Domain: 
    Bounding Coordinates: 
      West Bounding Coordinate: -120
      East Bounding Coordinate: -110
      North Bounding Coordinate: 60
      South Bounding Coordinate: 49
  Keywords: 
    Theme: 
      Theme Keyword Thesaurus: none
      Theme Keyword: bottomhole temperature
      Theme Keyword: data
      Theme Keyword: drillstem test
      Theme Keyword: geothermal
      Theme Keyword: hydrogeology
      Theme Keyword: phanerozoic
      Theme Keyword: tabular data
      Theme Keyword: temperature
      Theme Keyword: well log data
    Place: 
      Place Keyword Thesaurus: none
      Place Keyword: 72e
      Place Keyword: 72l
      Place Keyword: 72m
      Place Keyword: 73d
      Place Keyword: 73e
      Place Keyword: 73l
      Place Keyword: 73m
      Place Keyword: 74d
      Place Keyword: 74e
      Place Keyword: 74l
      Place Keyword: 74m
      Place Keyword: 82g
      Place Keyword: 82h
      Place Keyword: 82i
      Place Keyword: 82j
      Place Keyword: 82n
      Place Keyword: 82o
      Place Keyword: 82p
      Place Keyword: 83a
      Place Keyword: 83b
      Place Keyword: 83c
      Place Keyword: 83d
      Place Keyword: 83e
      Place Keyword: 83f
      Place Keyword: 83g
      Place Keyword: 83h
      Place Keyword: 83i
      Place Keyword: 83j
      Place Keyword: 83k
      Place Keyword: 83l
      Place Keyword: 83m
      Place Keyword: 83n
      Place Keyword: 83o
      Place Keyword: 83p
      Place Keyword: 84a
      Place Keyword: 84b
      Place Keyword: 84c
      Place Keyword: 84d
      Place Keyword: 84e
      Place Keyword: 84f
      Place Keyword: 84g
      Place Keyword: 84h
      Place Keyword: 84i
      Place Keyword: 84j
      Place Keyword: 84k
      Place Keyword: 84l
      Place Keyword: 84m
      Place Keyword: 84n
      Place Keyword: 84o
      Place Keyword: 84p
      Place Keyword: alberta
      Place Keyword: alberta basin
      Place Keyword: canada
  Access Constraints: Public
  Use Constraints: Acknowledgement of the Alberta Energy Regulator/Alberta Geological Survey as the originator/source of this information is required as described in the Open Government License - Alberta.
  Point of Contact: 
    Contact Information: 
      Contact Organization Primary: 
        Contact Organization: Alberta Geological Survey
        Contact Person: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Position: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Address: 
        Address Type: mailing and physical
        Address: Alberta Energy Regulator
        Address: 4th Floor, Twin Atria Building
        Address: 4999-98 Avenue NW
        City: Edmonton
        State or Province: Alberta
        Postal Code: T6B 2X3
        Country: Canada
      Contact Voice Telephone: (780) 638-4491
      Contact Facsimile Telephone: (780) 422-1459
      Contact Electronic Mail Address: AGS-Info@aer.ca
      Hours of Service: 8:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. and 1:00 p.m. to 4:30 p.m.
  Cross Reference: 
    Citation Information: 
      Originator: Alberta Energy Regulator
      Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
      Originator: Brinsky, J.
      Originator: Singh, A.
      Originator: Hauck, T.E.
      Originator: Grobe, M.
      Originator: Palombi, D.
      Publication Date: 2022
      Title: Temperature mapping of select geological strata in Alberta (gridded data, ASCII format)
      Geospatial Data Presentation Form: raster digital data
      Series Information: 
        Series Name: Digital Data
        Issue Identification: DIG 2021-0031
      Publication Information: 
        Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
        Publisher: Alberta Geological Survey
      Online Linkage: https://www.ags.aer.ca
  Cross Reference: 
    Citation Information: 
      Originator: Alberta Energy Regulator
      Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
      Originator: Brinsky, J.
      Originator: Singh, A.
      Originator: Hauck, T.E.
      Originator: Grobe, M.
      Originator: Palombi, D.
      Publication Date: 2022
      Title: Temperature Mapping of Select Devonian Strata in Alberta
      Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document
      Series Information: 
        Series Name: Open File Report
        Issue Identification: OFR 2021-05
      Publication Information: 
        Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
        Publisher: Alberta Geological Survey
      Other Citation Details: ISBN: 978-1-4601-5353-6
      Online Linkage: https://www.ags.aer.ca
  Cross Reference: 
    Citation Information: 
      Originator: Alberta Energy Regulator
      Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
      Originator: Brinsky, J.
      Originator: Singh, A.
      Originator: Hauck, T.E.
      Originator: Grobe, M.
      Originator: Palombi, D.
      Publication Date: 2022
      Title: Subsurface Temperature Model of Alberta: Point Cloud Data (tabular data, tab-delimited)
      Geospatial Data Presentation Form: tabular digital data
      Series Information: 
        Series Name: Digital Data
        Issue Identification: DIG 2021-0030
      Publication Information: 
        Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
        Publisher: Alberta Geological Survey
      Online Linkage: https://www.ags.aer.ca
Data Quality Information: 
  Attribute Accuracy: 
    Attribute Accuracy Report: Any errors in the original data were carried into this dataset and no systematic checking of attributes from original data sources was undertaken. Outlier data were removed using statistical culling.
  Logical Consistency Report: There may be more than one record for a UWI if multiple temperature sources for a well were obtained. This will be reflected in the UWI being duplicated. Geographic coordinates (latitude/longitude) may be the same for different wells because wells could have been recompleted.
  Completeness Report: All temperature measurements with sufficient information were selected from described sources. Null values are reported as -9999.
  Positional Accuracy: 
    Horizontal Positional Accuracy: 
      Horizontal Positional Accuracy Report: The locations of the oil and gas wells may be accurate to within millimetres depending on surveying standards at the time of drilling.
    Vertical Positional Accuracy: 
      Vertical Positional Accuracy Report: The location of intervals in oil and gas wells may be accurate to within millimetres in accordance with surveying standards at the time of drilling.

For the BHT logs, if the depth of the temperature measurement wasn't provided, the depth was estimated using the true vertical depth of the well (m). Depths from the Nieuwenhuis dataset were used as provided for data coming from vertical wells.  For deviated and horizontal wells, the depth was converted to the true vertical depth (m). For DSTs the depth of the temperature was approximated by using the mid point of the DST interval. The location of the DST intervals in oil and gas wells may be accurate to within millimetres in accordance with surveying standards at the time of drilling.
  Lineage: 
    Process Step: 
      Process Description: For a detailed description of the methodology refer to Section 3 in AGS Open File Report 2021-05: Temperature Mapping of Select Devonian Strata in Alberta. 

Temperature measurements were obtained from a previously unpublished database produced at the University of Alberta as part of a data sharing agreement with the Alberta Geological Survey (AGS) for the Nieuwenhuis et al. (2015) study (referred to as the ‘Nieuwenhuis dataset’). This dataset consists of temperatures from drillstem tests and annual pool pressure survey reports, as well as Horner-corrected wireline log bottomhole temperature (BHT) data.

For deviated and horizontal wells, depths were corrected to true vertical depth (metres).

Wireline log derived temperatures (BHTs) from LAS well log data, and temperatures from an AGS legacy database produced by manually transcribing log header data from microfiche logs were corrected using an Alberta-calibrated Harrison equation. These data were then combined with the Nieuwenhuis dataset and culled using a statistical approach as follows:

1) The data were modelled in ArcGIS Pro using the 3D empirical Bayesian kriging technique. The data were analyzed using cross-validation, where BHTs with a cross-validation error greater than 2.5 or less than –2.5 standard deviations from the mean error were removed.

2) The resulting data were then re-modelled using the same 3D empirical Bayesian kriging technique. The data were analyzed using cross-validation, where BHTs with a cross-validation error greater than 2.5 standard deviations from the mean error were removed.

3) The resulting data was then re-modelled using the same 3D empirical Bayesian kriging technique. Residuals were calculated (predicted temperature minus measured temperature), and temperature values from the Nieuwenhuis dataset and BHTs with a residual >5 °C or <-5 °C were removed. This single-iteration process removed temperature values with large discrepancies from the regional mean. Residuals recorded on the final dataset correspond to the final model, which was adjusted from the statistical culling model, and include some data points with final residuals >5 °C or <-5°C.

The resulting temperature database consists of 230 702 records.

Reference:
Nieuwenhuis, G., Lengyel, T., Majorowicz, J.A., Grobe, M., Rostron, B., Unsworth, M.J. and Weides, S. (2015): Regional-scale geothermal exploration using heterogeneous industrial temperature data; a case study from the Western Canadian Sedimentary Basin; in Proceedings of the World Geothermal Congress, April 16–24, 2015, Melbourne, Australia, p. 19–25.
      Process Date: 2021
Entity and Attribute Information: 
  Detailed Description: 
    Entity Type: 
      Entity Type Label: DIG 2021-0029
      Entity Type Definition: This dataset contains a compilation of subsurface temperature data used to create a 3D subsurface temperaure model and 2D temperature distribution maps for select strata in Alberta.
      Entity Type Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: UWI
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Unique identifier assigned by the AER to a licensed wellbore as described in AER Directive 059.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Lat_NAD83
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Latitude, NAD83 datum, decimal degrees north.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Long_NAD83
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Longitude, NAD83 datum, decimal degrees east.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Data_src
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Source of the temperature data, Log = temperature acquired from a wireline log header in Log ASCII Standard (LAS) format or read from a microfiche, and Nieuw = data acquired from the Nieuwenhuis dataset.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Src_type
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Type of the temperature measurement source where: A = annual pool pressure survey, D = drillstem test, E = Horner-corrected BHT data from the Nieuwenhuis dataset, LAS = well log header in Log ASCII standard format, MF = well log header on microfiche.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Depth_m
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Depth of the temperature measurement, in metres below kelly bushing.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: El_masl28
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Elevation of the temperature measurement, in metres above sea level, Canadian Geodetic Vertical Datum of 1928.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Temp_rec_C
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Recorded temperature, in degrees Celsius. This includes all measured data from drillstem tests and annual pool pressure surveys, as well as uncorrected bottomhole temperatures that did not have sufficient time series data for a Horner correction.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Temp_est_C
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Best estimate of the formation temperature, in degrees Celsius, used in the creation of the subsurface temperature model. This includes the measured data from drillstem tests and pool pressure surveys and the Horner-corrected bottomhole temperature data from the Nieuwenhuis dataset, as well as the bottomhole temperature data corrected with the Alberta-calibrated Harrison correction.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Residual_C
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Calculated difference, in degrees Celsius, between the modelled distribution of temperature and the best estimate of the formation temperature.

    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Publisher
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Definition: Organization that published the dataset.
Distribution Information: 
  Distributor: 
    Contact Information: 
      Contact Organization Primary: 
        Contact Organization: Alberta Geological Survey
        Contact Person: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Position: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Address: 
        Address Type: mailing and physical
        Address: Alberta Energy Regulator
        Address: 4th Floor, Twin Atria Building
        Address: 4999-98 Avenue NW
        City: Edmonton
        State or Province: Alberta
        Postal Code: T6B 2X3
        Country: Canada
      Contact Voice Telephone: (780) 638-4491
      Contact Facsimile Telephone: (780) 422-1459
      Contact Electronic Mail Address: AGS-Info@aer.ca
      Hours of Service: 8:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. and 1:00 p.m. to 4:30 p.m.
  Distribution Liability: The Alberta Energy Regulator / Alberta Geological Survey (AER/AGS) licenses this information under the Open Government License - Alberta. Any references to proprietary software in our documentation, and/or any use of proprietary data formats in our releases, do not constitute endorsement by the AER/AGS of any manufacturer's product.
Metadata Reference Information: 
  Metadata Date: 20220512
  Metadata Contact: 
    Contact Information: 
      Contact Organization Primary: 
        Contact Organization: Alberta Geological Survey
        Contact Person: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Position: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Address: 
        Address Type: mailing and physical
        Address: Alberta Energy Regulator
        Address: 4th Floor, Twin Atria Building
        Address: 4999-98 Avenue NW
        City: Edmonton
        State or Province: Alberta
        Postal Code: T6B 2X3
        Country: Canada
      Contact Voice Telephone: (780) 638-4491
      Contact Facsimile Telephone: (780) 422-1459
      Contact Electronic Mail Address: AGS-Info@aer.ca
      Hours of Service: 8:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. and 1:00 p.m. to 4:30 p.m.
  Metadata Standard Name: FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata
  Metadata Standard Version: FGDC-STD-001-1998
  Metadata Time Convention: local time
  Metadata Access Constraints: none
  Metadata Use Constraints: none
